<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The J*</title>
    <link>http://www.vorozco.com</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.vorozco.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>The J*, a blog about Java, JVM, JavaScript and Gentoo Linux</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 01:23:39 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 01:23:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>

    <item>
      <title>GuateJUG Tour 2015</title>
      <link>http://www.vorozco.com/blog/2015/GuateJUG-Tour-2015.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">blog/2015/GuateJUG-Tour-2015.html</guid>
      	<description>
	&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guate-jug.net&quot;&gt;GuateJUG&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;we arrived to our fifth year&lt;/strong&gt;, consequently I must start this post with a &quot;thanks to everybody that made this possible (developers, advocates, supporters, sponsors, friends, family, and other-UG)&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This year has been a special year for GuateJUG&lt;/strong&gt; and Java in general, in February we were very excited about being featured at &lt;a href=&quot;http://gtts.ehu.es/WDW/biblio/JavaMagazine/javamagazine20150102-dl.pdf&quot;&gt;Java Magazine&lt;/a&gt; (a little step for .gt developers, a great step for our user group), and as every inch of the web knows 2015 is the year of the 20 years of Java, another anniversary that came in hand to believe that 2015 is the year of Java reborn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hence, at GuateJUG we added to our regular activities a conference circuit called &lt;strong&gt;GuateJUG Tour&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/gtour2015.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/gtour2015.png&quot; alt=&quot;GuateJUG Tour&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As many of our activities, this is some kind of spontaneous tour, hence &lt;strong&gt;we&apos;ll be adding dates as new cities are confirmed&lt;/strong&gt; (Guatemala is a small country so it&apos;s possible to confirm in very short notice).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The tour started on September 26 and I&apos;m confirmed as a speaker in three cities, so &lt;strong&gt;I&apos;ll be collecting my slides in this post for quick reference&lt;/strong&gt; :).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Java 8: Más funcional que nunca&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/30AXtCu2ARI9hD&quot; width=&quot;425&quot; height=&quot;355&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;&quot; allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom:5px&quot;&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;//www.slideshare.net/tuxtor/java-8-ms-funcional-que-nunca&quot; title=&quot;Java 8: Más funcional que nunca&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Java 8: Más funcional que nunca&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;//www.slideshare.net/tuxtor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Víctor Orozco&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome</title>
      <link>http://www.vorozco.com/blog/2015/Welcome.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 8 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">blog/2015/Welcome.html</guid>
      	<description>
	&lt;p&gt;Hi, If you&apos;re reading this probably you are one of my few twitter followers, so thanks for your visit. For those that don&apos;t know me I wanna share a little story with you :).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an IT guy, I started my main website/blog &lt;a href=&quot;http://tuxtor.shekalug.org/&quot;&gt;El abismo de tux (in spanish)&lt;/a&gt; in 2006 during my college years, mostly as an experiment that grew as the blog phenoma exploded, gaining great experiences like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being featured in a nation-wide newspaper;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being invited to morning talk shows due my tech/politics rants;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Getting opportunities like my first job using my tech blog as a &quot;certification&quot; of my expertise in Unix and Java.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;So . . . what&apos;s the point of starting a new website in 2015?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I consider my old blog as a chronological reflection of my life experiences, like my stupidity at college, my involvement in FLOSS communities, my musical taste, EVERYTHING that I could talk about technology, politics, society, academia, the life in the countries where I&apos;ve lived (Guatemala, Brazil), and in recent years using it as an scratchpad of my day to day coding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During this year at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nabenik.com&quot;&gt;Nabenik&lt;/a&gt;, while I was struggling to improve my coding skills I noticed that most if not all the times I search for tech content exclusively in English, and I&apos;ve noticed also a debacle on my readers due the change of focus at my old blog. because I simply killed some topics that I don&apos;t care anymore (politics, Free Software as a social movement, the country where I live), so I&apos;ve decided that is time to put the &quot;Tux Abyss&quot; in mantainance mode.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Killing a website is more difficult than it looks, specially a website that has been online since 2006, however at this point of my life/carreer I&apos;d like to share deeper facts and knowlege about fewer topics, specially:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gentoo Linux and Unix in General&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JVM Languages (Java, JavaScript)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;That&apos;s why I&apos;m welcoming you to &quot;The J*&quot;, the name is inspired in three facts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I write code in JVM Languages (specially Java) and JavaScript on daily basis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was born in June&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The second name of a child that means a lot to me starts with J&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this site and considering my past experiences with Wordpress and Jekyll . . . I decided to try &lt;a href=&quot;http://jbake.org/&quot;&gt;JBake&lt;/a&gt;, mainly because I&apos;m familiar with Gradle, and for me is easier to write posts in markdown. Also because I fell in love with the results at &lt;a href=&quot;http://vertx.io&quot;&gt;Vert.x&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hawkular.org/&quot;&gt;Hawkular&lt;/a&gt; to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this time this blog is hosted at GitHub pages being built by &lt;a href=&quot;https://travis-ci.org/tuxtor/the-j&quot;&gt;Travis-CI&lt;/a&gt; with gradle, saving me hosting costs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think that starting a web site in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jacquesmattheij.com/aol-20&quot;&gt;AOL 2.0&lt;/a&gt; era is some kind of digital rebellion, so please grab a seat and feel free to drop comments :).&lt;/p&gt;
	</description>
    </item>

  </channel> 
</rss>
