<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The J*</title>
    <link>http://www.vorozco.com</link>
    <atom:link href="http://www.vorozco.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>The J*, a blog about Java, JVM, JavaScript and Gentoo Linux</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <pubDate>Tue, 5 Jan 2016 22:04:39 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 5 Jan 2016 22:04:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>

    <item>
      <title>20 years of Java in Java One and Java Day Guatemala</title>
      <link>http://www.vorozco.com/blog/2015/2015-11-16-20-years-Java-5-years-GuateJUG.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">blog/2015/2015-11-16-20-years-Java-5-years-GuateJUG.html</guid>
      	<description>
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/java20/java20.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/java20/java20.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Java 20&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For me &lt;strong&gt;2015 hacktivism is officially closed&lt;/strong&gt;, this year I had the opportunity to attend my first Java One and met some of my development heroes, folks from another JUGs, being trapped at Patricia&apos;s hurricane (no kidding), and bring a huge amount of Java t-shirts to Guatemala. I must say thanks to the people that made this trip possible, special acknowledgments to Nichole Scott from Oracle, my peers at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nabenik.com&quot;&gt;Nabenik&lt;/a&gt; that gratefully sponsored my trip and the Guatemala Java User Group for allowing me to take advantage of the Java One ticket :-D.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think that every techie has a list of conferences to attend before die, as 2015 my top five is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JavaOne (2015 finally)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gentoo Miniconf&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OSCON&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Forum Internacional de Sofware Livre - FISL (2013 as a speaker yey!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Convención de Informatica Guatemala (2005 - now dead, but it made the list for nostalgia)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although I had some health issues due stress, Java One and San Francisco were lifetime experiences. As each conference I&apos;ve attended, it has its goods and bads but in general &lt;strong&gt;you can feel a strong sense of community between attendants&lt;/strong&gt;, from Pivotal to Red Hat (and Microsoft), from the peer that shares a beer with you and turns out to be a Java Champion to the people that speaks another languages with you, Java One is about community making awesome things in IT. Programming languages aren&apos;t eternal but I can state that the differential factor that raised 20-year languages like Java and JavaScript among the others is the community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Random photos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;fotorama&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/java20/IMG_20151023_151334.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/java20/IMG_20151023_185726.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/java20/IMG_20151024_104546.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/java20/IMG_20151024_122253.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/java20/IMG_20151025_133147.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/java20/IMG_20151025_152920.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/java20/IMG_20151026_194945.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a different scale but in the same sense of community, the Guatemala Java User Group held its yearly conference &lt;strong&gt;Java Day Guatemala&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve been involved directly in the organization of 2 Java Days and spoken in three. As I said in our keynote, for me &lt;strong&gt;GuateJUG has been the most successful user group&lt;/strong&gt; where I&apos;ve participated. Characterized by pragmatism, openness and community structure since its inception, GuateJUG became one of the strongest user groups in Central America, the integration between industry, academia, Open Source communities, Free Software communities and HR people looking for the next generation of developers is unique.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As a special occasion &lt;strong&gt;we held a traditional birthday celebration&lt;/strong&gt;, including birthday cake and mexican piñatas. It was great to share words with some old friends and meet new IT enthusiasts, as a matter of fact we also sang &quot;Happy birthday Java and happy birthday GuateJUG&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Video and some more random photos:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;420&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/u7o0XShv79E&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;fotorama&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/java20/11226069_1060642347287731_5812305256213579668_o.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/java20/12238470_1060643013954331_2349556758532275784_o.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/java20/12244626_1060641943954438_3151222273500737324_o.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/java20/12265953_1060642613954371_2213430104867139963_o.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/java20/_DSC0452.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I hope to see you the next year in Java One and Java Day :-).&lt;/p&gt;
	</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>[Book Review] Java EE 7 Essentials, O’Reilly</title>
      <link>http://www.vorozco.com/blog/2015/2015-11-12-Java-Essentials-Book-Review.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">blog/2015/2015-11-12-Java-Essentials-Book-Review.html</guid>
      	<description>
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/gf-essentials.gif&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/gf-essentials.gif&quot; alt=&quot;JavaEE 7 Essentials Cover&quot; style=&quot;width: 150px;&quot;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1&gt;About the book&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Pages: 362
Publisher: O’Reilly Media
Release: Aug 2013
ISBN-10: 978-1-4493-7016-9
ISBN-13: 1-4493-7016-0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Book details&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I received this book as a part of the now dead O&apos;Reilly users group program&lt;/strong&gt;. When I asked for this book I was specially interested due comments from my development peers . . . and most importantly because I was in the middle of a Software Architecture definition.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&apos;m writing this review after 7 months of using it on daily basis, basically because our development stack is composed by AngularJS on the front-end and JavaEE 7 on the back-end (with a huge bias to the Hat company). At the office we have a small books collection (because IT books are pretty dead after five years), and &lt;strong&gt;Aurun&apos;s book is our prefered book&lt;/strong&gt; for the &quot;Java EE 7 rescue kit&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;If I have to choose &lt;strong&gt;two adjectives for this book I must say &quot;quick and versatile&quot;&lt;/strong&gt;, this book deserves all of its fame because it has the balance between a good reference book and a user friendly introductory book, most of the IT books don&apos;t achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t wanna copy the index page but I have the following &lt;strong&gt;favorite chapters&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Servlets&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;RESTFul Web Services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SOAP Web Services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JSON Processing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enterprise Java Beans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Context and Dependency Injection&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bean Validation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Java Transactions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Java Persistence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Most of the book samples are based on Glassfish, and is easy to guess why looking at the publication date. However, talking from my true-heavy-metal-monkey-developer-architect experience, &lt;strong&gt;this book uses only pure JavaEE 7 apis&lt;/strong&gt; and I&apos;ve been able to run/use the samples on Wildfly without issues.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For those that are looking a good book for JavaEE 7 development, on any of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oracle.com/technetwork/java/javaee/overview/compatibility-jsp-136984.html&quot;&gt;certified Java EE 7 servers&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;this is a must&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Highlights&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Good balance between tutorial and reference.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Few content compared to the Java EE Tutorial but still in the point.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The samples should work on any Java EE 7 server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Could be better&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WebSockets section is small in relation to the other chapters, it feels incomplete.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The cover brings to my mind the good old days when Glassfish was that application server that everybody is talking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
	</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GuateJUG Tour 2015 First Leg</title>
      <link>http://www.vorozco.com/blog/2015/GuateJUG-Tour-2015-First-Leg.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">blog/2015/GuateJUG-Tour-2015-First-Leg.html</guid>
      	<description>
	&lt;p&gt;As I described &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/2015/GuateJUG-Tour-2015.html&quot;&gt;previously&lt;/a&gt;, GuateJUG held a conference circuit promoting its yearly conference &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guate-jug.net/javaday2015&quot;&gt;Java Day Guatemala 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This activity was motivated by &lt;a href=&quot;https://community.oracle.com/community/java/javas-20th-anniversary&quot;&gt;Java&apos;s 20th anniversary&lt;/a&gt; and specially due &lt;strong&gt;GuateJUG&apos;s 5th anniversary&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;So... how do you achieve a tour that traverses Guatemala?. Easy, with the right sponsors and contacts :).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An special acknowledgment&lt;/strong&gt; for the people that made this first leg possible:&lt;br/&gt;- Jorge Cajas (Universidad de San Carlos de Guatemala)&lt;br/&gt;- Dhaby Xiloj (Universidad Rafael Landivar - Quetzaltenango)&lt;br/&gt;- Rene Alvarado (Universidad de San Carlos de Guatemala - Chiquimula)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In this first leg (not the only one . . . I hope) GuateJUG team went &lt;strong&gt;from the center of the country to the east and later to the west&lt;/strong&gt;, like in this ugly map:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/guatejugtour2015/map.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/guatejugtour2015/map.png&quot; alt=&quot;GuateJUG Tour&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Covering the following topics&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;First conference&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Place: Universidad de San Carlos de Guatemala - Guatemala City&lt;br/&gt;* Java 8: Functional programming principles (me)&lt;br/&gt;* 20 years of Java (Wences Arana - DebianGt)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Second conference&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Place: Universidad Rafael Landivar - Quetzaltenango&lt;br/&gt;* Source code control with Git - (me)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Third conference&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Place: Universidad de San Carlos de Guatemala - Chiquimula&lt;br/&gt;* HTML5 applications with Java EE 7 and AngularJS - (me)&lt;br/&gt;* Android 101 - (Mercedes Wyss - GuateJUG)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Random photos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;fotorama&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/guatejugtour2015/1.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/guatejugtour2015/2.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/guatejugtour2015/3.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/guatejugtour2015/4.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/guatejugtour2015/5.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/guatejugtour2015/6.jpg&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/guatejugtour2015/7.jpg&quot;&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some years ago &lt;strong&gt;I did a similar tour with the FLOSS community in my college years&lt;/strong&gt;. The sensation of going back to the same cities, hanging out with good old friends and other new friends is always pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every time anyone asks me why I do this, &lt;strong&gt;I have the same answer&lt;/strong&gt; &quot;why not? At least each time I know the country a little bit more :)&quot;. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;With this I&apos;m in the best mood for Java Day Guatemala and most importantly to attend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oracle.com/javaone/index.html&quot;&gt;Java One 2015&lt;/a&gt; willing to collaborate with some User Groups activities, I hope to see many of you in both conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
	</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GuateJUG Tour 2015</title>
      <link>http://www.vorozco.com/blog/2015/GuateJUG-Tour-2015.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">blog/2015/GuateJUG-Tour-2015.html</guid>
      	<description>
	&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.guate-jug.net&quot;&gt;GuateJUG&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;we arrived to our fifth year&lt;/strong&gt;, consequently I must start this post with a &quot;thanks to everybody that made this possible (developers, advocates, supporters, sponsors, friends, family, and other-UG)&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This year has been a special year for GuateJUG&lt;/strong&gt; and Java in general, in February we were very excited about being featured at &lt;a href=&quot;http://gtts.ehu.es/WDW/biblio/JavaMagazine/javamagazine20150102-dl.pdf&quot;&gt;Java Magazine&lt;/a&gt; (a little step for .gt developers, a great step for our user group), and as every inch of the web knows 2015 is the year of the 20 years of Java, another anniversary that came in hand to believe that 2015 is the year of Java reborn.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hence, at GuateJUG we added to our regular activities a conference circuit called &lt;strong&gt;GuateJUG Tour&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/images/posts/gtour2015.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/gtour2015.png&quot; alt=&quot;GuateJUG Tour&quot; style=&quot;width: 300px;&quot;/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As many of our activities, this is some kind of spontaneous tour, hence &lt;strong&gt;we&apos;ll be adding dates as new cities are confirmed&lt;/strong&gt; (Guatemala is a small country so it&apos;s possible to confirm in very short notice).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The tour started on September 26 and I&apos;m confirmed as a speaker in three cities, so &lt;strong&gt;I&apos;ll be collecting my slides in this post for quick reference&lt;/strong&gt; :).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Java 8: Más funcional que nunca&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/30AXtCu2ARI9hD&quot; width=&quot;425&quot; height=&quot;355&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;&quot; allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom:5px&quot;&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;//www.slideshare.net/tuxtor/java-8-ms-funcional-que-nunca&quot; title=&quot;Java 8: Más funcional que nunca&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Java 8: Más funcional que nunca&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;//www.slideshare.net/tuxtor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Víctor Orozco&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Git 101 (with Java)&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/H4g9lRHrc63bzj&quot; width=&quot;425&quot; height=&quot;355&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;&quot; allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom:5px&quot;&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;//www.slideshare.net/tuxtor/introduccin-a-git-git-101&quot; title=&quot;Introducción a Git (Git 101)&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Introducción a Git (Git 101)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;//www.slideshare.net/tuxtor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Víctor Orozco&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h1&gt;Aplicaciones HTML5 con AngularJS y JavaEE&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/EVtupsoyepJrX3&quot; width=&quot;425&quot; height=&quot;355&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; marginwidth=&quot;0&quot; marginheight=&quot;0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; style=&quot;border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;&quot; allowfullscreen&gt; &lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom:5px&quot;&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;//www.slideshare.net/tuxtor/inciando-con-angularjs-y-javaee-7&quot; title=&quot;Inciando con AngularJS y JavaEE 7&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Inciando con AngularJS y JavaEE 7&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; from &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;//www.slideshare.net/tuxtor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Víctor Orozco&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Welcome</title>
      <link>http://www.vorozco.com/blog/2015/Welcome.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 8 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">blog/2015/Welcome.html</guid>
      	<description>
	&lt;p&gt;Hi, If you&apos;re reading this probably you are one of my few twitter followers, so thanks for your visit. For those that don&apos;t know me I wanna share a little story with you :).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As an IT guy, I started my main website/blog &lt;a href=&quot;http://tuxtor.shekalug.org/&quot;&gt;El abismo de tux (in spanish)&lt;/a&gt; in 2006 during my college years, mostly as an experiment that grew as the blog phenoma exploded, gaining great experiences like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being featured in a nation-wide newspaper;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Being invited to morning talk shows due my tech/politics rants;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Getting opportunities like my first job using my tech blog as a &quot;certification&quot; of my expertise in Unix and Java.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;So . . . what&apos;s the point of starting a new website in 2015?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I consider my old blog as a chronological reflection of my life experiences, like my stupidity at college, my involvement in FLOSS communities, my musical taste, EVERYTHING that I could talk about technology, politics, society, academia, the life in the countries where I&apos;ve lived (Guatemala, Brazil), and in recent years using it as an scratchpad of my day to day coding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;During this year at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nabenik.com&quot;&gt;Nabenik&lt;/a&gt;, while I was struggling to improve my coding skills I noticed that most if not all the times I search for tech content exclusively in English, and I&apos;ve noticed also a debacle on my readers due the change of focus at my old blog. because I simply killed some topics that I don&apos;t care anymore (politics, Free Software as a social movement, the country where I live), so I&apos;ve decided that is time to put the &quot;Tux Abyss&quot; in mantainance mode.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Killing a website is more difficult than it looks, specially a website that has been online since 2006, however at this point of my life/carreer I&apos;d like to share deeper facts and knowlege about fewer topics, specially:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gentoo Linux and Unix in General&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JVM Languages (Java, JavaScript)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;That&apos;s why I&apos;m welcoming you to &quot;The J*&quot;, the name is inspired in three facts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I write code in JVM Languages (specially Java) and JavaScript on daily basis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I was born in June&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The second name of a child that means a lot to me starts with J&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For this site and considering my past experiences with Wordpress and Jekyll . . . I decided to try &lt;a href=&quot;http://jbake.org/&quot;&gt;JBake&lt;/a&gt;, mainly because I&apos;m familiar with Gradle, and for me is easier to write posts in markdown. Also because I fell in love with the results at &lt;a href=&quot;http://vertx.io&quot;&gt;Vert.x&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hawkular.org/&quot;&gt;Hawkular&lt;/a&gt; to name a few.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;At this time this blog is hosted at GitHub pages being built by &lt;a href=&quot;https://travis-ci.org/tuxtor/the-j&quot;&gt;Travis-CI&lt;/a&gt; with gradle, saving me hosting costs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think that starting a web site in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jacquesmattheij.com/aol-20&quot;&gt;AOL 2.0&lt;/a&gt; era is some kind of digital rebellion, so please grab a seat and feel free to drop comments :).&lt;/p&gt;
	</description>
    </item>

  </channel> 
</rss>
